Robotics is a really cool and important direction for the future,
机器人学是未来一个非常酷和重要的方向，
I I really believe that we are moving towards a world,
我相信我们正在走向一个这样一个世界，
where so many routine tasks are taken off your plate,
很多日常工作都从你的盘子里消失，
fresh produce turn turns up at your doorsteps delivered by drones,
新鲜的农产品出现在你的门口，由无人机运送，
garbage bins take themselves out,
垃圾桶会自己倒出来，
smart infrastructure ensures that the garbage gets removed,
智能基础设施确保垃圾被清除，
robots help with recycling, with shelving, with cleaning windows,
机器人帮助回收、搁置和清洁窗户，
robots can do so many physical things for us.
机器人可以为我们做很多物理上的事情，
And by the way,
顺便问一下，
can you count how many robots there are in this, in this image,
你能数一下在这张图片中有多少个机器人吗，
anybody want to take a guess,
有人想猜一下吗，
how many robots do I have in this image?
在这张图中，我有多少个机器人？
Okay, that, so that's, that's really close,
好的，这很接近了，
it, it turns out it's 19,
结果是 19 个，
so here are all the robots,
所有的机器人都在这里，
we have flying robots,
我们有会飞的机器人，
we have cars,
我们有汽车，
we have shopping cart robots,
我们有购物车机器人，
we have robots that carry,
我们有搬运的机器人，
we have robots that shelf,
我们在那个架子上有机器人，
we have robots that clean.
我们有清洁机器人。
And so I really believe,
所以，我真的相信，
that in the future we will have AI assistance,
在未来，我们将有人工智能的帮助，
whether they are embodied or not,
无论它们是否体现，
to act as our guardian angels
作为我们的守护天使，
to provide advice to ensure that,
提供建议，以确保，
we maximize and optimize our lives,
我们最大化和优化我们的生活，
to live well and work effectively.
生活得好和工作有效。
And these agents will help us with cognitive and physical work.
这些代理将帮助我们进行认知和体力工作。
And so today, we can say that,
所以，今天我们可以说，
with AI we will see such a wide breadth of applications,
有了人工智能，我们将看到如此广泛的应用，
for instance, these technologies have the potential to reduce and eliminate car accidents,
例如，这些技术有可能减少和消除车祸，
they have the potential to better diagnose monitor and treat disease
它们有可能更好地诊断监测和治疗疾病，
as you have seen in some of the previous lectures,
正如你在之前的一些讲座中看到的那样，
we, these technologies have the potential
这些技术有可能，
to keep your information private and safe,
保持你的信息隐私和安全，
to transport people and goods more effectively and faster and cheaper,
更有效、更快、更便宜地运输人员和货物，
to really make it easier to communicate globally by providing instantaneous translations
通过提供即时翻译来真正使全球沟通变得更容易，
to, to develop education to everyone,
为每个人发展教育，
to allow human workers to focus on big picture tasks
让人类工作人员专注于宏大的任务，
with machines taking on the routine tasks.
让机器承担日常任务。
And so this future is really enabled by three interconnected fields
所以，这一未来是由三个相互关联的领域实现的，
and on one hand we have robots,
一方面我们有机器人，
now robots, I like to think of robots as as the machines,
我喜欢把机器人看作是一台机器，
that put computing in motion
它让计算运转起来，
and give give our our machines in the world the ability to navigate and to manipulate the world,
让我们在世界上的机器具有导航和操纵世界的能力，
we have artificial intelligence,
我们有人工智能，
which enables machines to see To hear and to communicate and to make decisions like humans,
它能让机器像人一样看到、听到、交流和做出决定，
and then we have machine learning,
然后我们有机器学习，
and to me, machine learning is about learning from and making predictions on data,
对我来说，机器学习是关于从数据中学习并做出预测，
and this, this kind of application of machine learning is broad,
机器学习的这种应用是广泛的，
it, it applies to cognitive tasks,
它适用于认知任务，
it applies to physical tasks,
它适用于物理任务，
but regardless of the tasks,
但不管任务是什么，
we can characterize how machine learning works as using data
我们可以描述机器学习如何使用数据工作，
to answer questions that are either descriptive, predictive or prescriptive,
来回答描述性、预测性或说明性的问题，
so you can look at data
所以你可以查看数据，
to see what happened or to see what is this,
看看发生了什么，或者这是什么，
you can look at data
你可以查看数据，
to see what will happen in the future
看看未来会发生什么，
and what the world might look like in the future,
未来世界可能是什么样子，
or you can use data to ask where should I go, what should I do.
或者你可以用数据来问我应该去哪里，我应该做什么。
And so when we think about these questions in the context of a robot,
所以，当我们在机器人的背景下思考这些问题时，
we have to, we have to kind of get on the same page about what a robot is.
我们必须在机器人是什么的问题上达成一致。
And, and so think of a robot as a programmable mechanical device,
所以，可以把机器人想象成一个可编程的机械设备，
that takes input with its sensors,
它通过传感器接受输入，
reasons about this input,
对输入进行推理，
and then generates an action in the physical world.
然后在物理世界中产生一个动作。
And robots are made of a body and the brain,
机器人是由身体和大脑组成的，
the body consisting of actuators and sensors
身体由执行器和传感器组成，
determine the range of tasks that the robot can do,
决定了机器人可以完成的任务范围，
so the robot can only do what its body is capable of doing,
机器人只能做它的身体能够做的事情，
robot on wheels will not be able to do the task of climbing stairs,
轮子上的机器人不能完成爬楼梯的任务，
so we have to think about that body,
所以我们必须考虑那个身体，
and we have at,
我们有[]，
we have a lot of machine learning based research,
我们有很多基于机器学习的研究，
that allows us to that that examines,
使我们能够研究，
how to design optimally a robot body for a particular task.
如何为特定任务优化设计机器人身体。
Now, in order for the body to do what it's meant to do,
现在，为了让身体做它应该做的事情，
we need the brain,
我们需要大脑，
we need the machine learning and the reason and the decision making engine,
我们需要机器学习，需要推理和决策引擎，
and this is what we are going to talk about today.
这就是我们今天要谈论的。
Now in the context of robots,
现在，在机器人的背景下，
we have three types of learning
我们有三种类型的学习，
and you have seen different aspects of these methodologies throughout the course.
你们在整个课程中看到了这些方法的不同方面。
We have supervised learning,
我们有监督学习，
and so in this, in this method of learning,
在这个学习方法中，
eh, we use data to have to find the relationship between input and output.
我们要用数据来找出投入产出之间的关系。
We have unsupervised learning
我们有无监督学习，
and in the context of unsupervised learning,
在无监督学习的背景下，
we can use data to have patterns,
我们可以使用数据来获得模式，
to find patterns and classifications of the data.
找到数据的模式和分类。
And then we have reinforcement learning,
然后我们有强化学习，
which is about learning to perform a task by maximizing reward.
这是关于通过最大化奖励来学习执行任务。
So for robots,
所以对于机器人来说，
we end up with a cycle that most often consists of three steps,
我们最终得到了一个最经常由三个步骤组成的循环，
we have perception, a perception step,
我们有感知的步骤，
we have a planning and reasoning step
我们有计划和推理的步骤，
and we have an action step.
我们有行动的步骤。
And so this is what we are going to talk about today.
这就是我们今天要讨论的问题。
So let me start with some examples
所以让我从一些例子开始，
of how we can use machine learning to enhance the perception capability of robots.
我们如何使用机器学习来增强机器人的感知能力。
And so this is addressing the question what is this,
所以这就解决了这是什么的问题，
and this question is really important,
这个问题真的很重要，
because for instance, training robot cars to recognize all objects on roads,
因为比如说，训练机器人汽车识别道路上的所有物体，
including ducks, cars, people,
包括鸭子，汽车，人，
is really critical for autonomous driving
对于自动驾驶来说是非常关键的，
and so how does this work,
那么这是如何工作的，
well, let me let me give you a high level view
好的，让我给你一个高层次的视角，
of how a robot car can actually recognize the scene.
看看机器人汽车是如何真正识别场景的。
So, in order to, in order to use deep learning for the perception task of robots,
所以，为了把深度学习用于机器人的感知任务，
we use data, this is manually labeled data,
我们使用数据，这是手动标记的数据，
that gets fed into a convolutional neural network
输入卷积神经网络，
and then the labels are used to classify what the data is,
然后使用这些标记来对数据进行分类，
so for instance for this image,
例如，对于这张图像，
we may have classifications like car, duck road
我们可能会有像汽车、鸭子、路这样的分类，
and we do this,
我们这样做，
so that when the system when the car sees a new image,
当系统看到新的图像时，
for example this one,
例如这张，
the car could say, oh, this is this is duck's road,
汽车可能会说，哦，这是鸭子路，
now in order to, in order to actually provide solutions for this object classification problem,
现在，为了真正为这个对象分类问题提供解决方案，
we have to, we have to employ multiple algorithms
我们必须使用多种算法，
and the first algorithm that we have to employ is called image segmentation,
我们必须使用的第一个算法称为图像分割，
in image segmentation, we take as we take inputs as input images
在图像分割中，我们把输入当作输入图像，
and we group together the pixels that belong to the same object in the image,
然后属于图像中同一对象的像素组合在一起，
and this is a kind of a lexical step,
这是一种词汇步骤，
and then we need to label and recognize these images,
然后我们需要标记和识别这些图像，
this is a semantic step,
这是一个语义步骤，
and so the exciting thing is that,
令人兴奋的是，
we already have very good algorithms,
我们已经有了非常好的算法，
that that can segment images very fast,
可以非常快地分割图像，
so, we can, we can do this, we can do this,
所以，我们可以这样做，
so we can, we can take an image
我们可以[拍摄]一张图像，
and we can find the object in the image very fast,
我们可以非常快地在图像中找到物体，
we don't know what the objects are,
我们不知道这些物体是什么，
so in order to know what the objects are,
所以为了知道这些物体是什么，
well, you know what we do, right,
你知道我们做了什么，
so we employ thousands of people to label the objects that we have.
我们雇佣了数千人来为我们拥有的物品做标注，
And so this is exciting,
所以这是令人兴奋的，
but, but labeling is a very labor intensive activity
但是标注是一项非常劳动密集型的活动，
and a significant challenge to machine learning,
对机器学习来说是一个巨大的挑战，
let's keep this thought for later.
让我们把这个想法留到以后再考虑。
Now the the most popular benchmark for measuring the accuracy of image classification is ImageNet
现在最流行的衡量图像分类准确性的基准是 ImageNet ，
and here we see the leaderboards of imageet
这里我们看到 ImageNet 的排行榜，
and we see performance of various, variations of, of image classification algorithms,
我们看到各种图像分类算法变体的性能，
that perform well into ninety, ninety percent accuracy
性能很好地达到了 90% 的准确率，
and this is really quite exciting,
这真的非常令人兴奋，
it's exciting,
这很令人兴奋，
but if those algorithms were to run on a car,
但如果这些算法在汽车上运行，
that's not good enough,
这还不够好，
because, because the car is a safety critical system
因为因为汽车是一个安全关键系统，
and in fact we cannot afford to have any errors
事实上我们不能有任何错误，
in how images get recognized in the car, on the car,
在汽车图像识别方面，
here's an example of of an object object detector that is running on on a car
这是一个运行在汽车上的物体探测器的例子，
and we we see the image from three cameras,
我们可以看到三个摄像头拍摄的图像，
there is a camera pointing forward,
有一个摄像头指向前方，
there is a camera pointing to the left,
有一个摄像头指向左边，
there is a camera pointing to the right
有一个摄像头指向右边，
and so you can see that the car takes this, this input
所以你可以看到这辆车接受了这个输入，
and it does pretty well,
它做得很好，
see there's a blue car,
那里有一辆蓝色的汽车，
there are some bicyclists,
那里有一些骑自行车的人，
there are, there's a bicyclist,
有个骑自行车的，
here's another car,
还有一辆车，
so the system does pretty well
所以这个系统做得很好，
and manages to find the gap in the road to make a turn,
设法找到了道路的缺口来转弯，
but it's not 100% correct,
但它并不是百分之百正确的，
so in particular there is this moving truck
特别是这辆移动的卡车，
and when this moving and when the image of the moving truck is passed through,
当当移动的卡车的图像通过时，
the object recognition piece of the system,
这个系统的物体识别部分，
we, we end up with a lot of interesting things,
我们最终得到了很多有趣的东西，
[] is recognized as a fence,
[]被认为是一道栅栏，
so these are, these are the kinds of extreme errors
这些是极端错误的类型，
or the way we denote them, corner cases,
或者我们表示它们的方式，即边界条件，
that we need to pay attention to when we train machine learning,
在我们训练机器学习时，我们需要注意的，
for safety critical applications, like driving.
对于安全关键型应用，如驾驶。
Well, it turns out that in fact,
事实证明，
if you use deep neural network solutions for image classification,
如果你使用深度神经网络解决方案来进行图像分类，
the the solutions work really well,
这些解决方案效果非常好，
because they are trained on a huge dataset ImageNet,
因为它们是在一个巨大的数据集 ImageNet 上进行训练的，
but the solutions capture more than the essence of the object,
但解决方案捕捉到的不仅仅是对象的本质，
the solutions also capture the context in which the object appears,
这些解决方案还捕获对象出现的上下文，
and so MIT researchers,
所以 MIT 的研究人员，
lead by Josh Tenenbaum and Boris Katz,
由 Josh Tenenbaum 和 Boris Katz 带领，
did an experiment a few years ago,
在几年前做了一个实验，
where they took regular objects,
他们用普通物体，
and they put them in a different context,
他们把它们放在不同的背景下，
so, for instance, they took their shoes and put them on the bed,
例如，他们把鞋子放在床上，
they took the pots and pens and put them in the bathroom,
他们拿起花盆和钢笔，放在浴室里，
and with a significant change in context,
随着环境的显著变化，
the performance of the top performing ImageNet algorithms dropped by as much as 40-50%,
性能最好的 ImageNet 算法的性能下降了 40%-50% ，
which is really extraordinary.
这真的是非同寻常。
And I'm sharing this with you,
我与你们分享这一点，
not to discourage you from using these algorithms,
不是为了阻止你们使用这些算法，
but to point out that,
而是要指出，
when you, when you deploy an algorithm,
当你部署一个算法时，
and especially when you deploy it in a safety critical application,
特别是当你把它部署在一个安全关键的应用程序中时，
it's important to understand the scope of the algorithm,
理解这个算法的范围是很重要的，
it's important to understand,
重要的是要了解，
what works and what doesn't work,
什么是有效的，什么无效的，
when you can apply the algorithm
什么时候可以应用算法，
and you when you shouldn't apply the the algorithm.
什么时候不应该应用算法。
And so, so keep this in mind
所以，请记住这一点，
as you think about deploying or building and deploying deep neural network solutions.
当你考虑构建或部署深度神经网络解决方案时。
There's another thing that is very critical for autonomous driving and for robots,
还有一件事对自动驾驶和机器人非常关键，
you have heard a beautiful lecture on adversarial attacks,
你已经听过一节关于对抗性攻击的精彩讲座，
well, it turns out, you can attack very easily,
事实证明，你可以非常容易地攻击，
the images that get fed from the camera streams of cars to the decision making engine of the car,
从汽车摄像头流到汽车决策引擎的图像，
and in fact, it's quite easy to take a stop sign
事实上，很容易拿起停车标志，
and perturb it a little bit, perturb it,
稍微扰乱它，
in, in such a way that you can't even tell with the naked eye,
以一种你甚至用肉眼都看不出的方式，
that there is a difference between the two images,
这两个图像之间有区别，
and with those small perturbations,
有了这些小的扰动，
you can turn the stop sign into a yield sign,
你可以把停车标志变成一个让行标志，
and you can imagine what kind of chaos this would create on a, on a physical road.
你可以想象这会在物理道路上造成什么样的混乱。
So machine learning is very powerful for building perception systems for robots,
所以，机器学习在为机器人构建感知系统方面非常强大，
but as we employ machine learning in the context of robots,
但是，当我们在机器人的环境中使用机器学习时，
it's important to keep in mind the scope,
重要的是记住它们范围，
when they work, when they don't work,
什么时候工作，什么时候不工作，
and then it's important to think about
然后，重要的是要考虑，
what might, what kind of guardrails we might put in place at the decision time,
在决策时我们可能会设置什么样的护栏，
so that we have robust behavior.
这样我们就有了健壮的行为。
So what could we do,
那么，我们能做些什么呢，
about the possibility of adversarial perturbations on the stop sign.
对于停车标志上可能出现的对抗性干扰。
Well, let's talk a little bit about decision making
好的，让我们来讨论一下决策，
and let's talk about how the car figures out what to do given input.
然后我们来谈谈汽车是如何计算出在给定输入的情况下要做什么的。
Reinforcement learning is causing a huge revolution in robotics,
强化学习正在引发机器人学的一场巨大革命，
and so and why is that,
那么为什么会这样，
well, the reason reinforcement learning is causing a huge revolution in robotics
强化学习之所以在机器人学中引发一场巨大的革命，
is because we have built fast simulation systems and simulation methodologies,
是因为我们已经建立了快速的模拟系统和模拟方法，
that allow us to run thousands of simulations in parallel
允许我们并行运行数千次模拟，
in order to train a reinforcement learning policy,
以便训练强化学习策略，
and we are also decreasing the gap between the hardware platforms and the simulation engines.
我们也缩小了硬件平台和仿真引擎之间的差距。
So you have seen reinforcement learning earlier in the in the boot camp,
所以你在课程早期已经看到了强化学习，
and so reinforcement learning is concerned with
所以强化学习关注的是，
how intelligent agents ought to take action in an environment
智能代理应该如何在环境中采取行动，
in order to maximize the notion of a cumulative reward.
以便最大化累积奖励的概念。
And so reinforcement learning is really about learning to act,
所以，强化学习实际上就是学习行动，
and this differs from supervised learning
这与监督学习的不同之处在于
is not needing a labeled input or is not needing labeled input, output pairs,
不需要标记的输入或不需要标记的输入输出对，
so in this example,
所以，在这个例子中，
the agent has to learn to avoid fire
代理必须学会避免火灾，
and it's very simple,
这很简单，
it gets a negative reward, if it goes to fire
如果它着火了，它会得到负的奖励，
and it gets a positive reward, when it gets to water,
当它到达水中时，它会得到正的奖励，
and that's essentially what what this approach is like,
这就是这种方法的本质，
you, you do trial and error
你不断地尝试和犯错，
and, and eventually the positive rewards dominate the negative rewards
最终，积极的回报主导了消极的回报，
and that that directs the, the agent towards the, the best action.
这将引导代理人朝着最好的行动前进。
And so here is an example,
这是一个例子，
where we have a reinforcement learning agent,
我们有一个强化学习代理，
that is trying to drive on a racetrack
它试图在赛道上驾驶，
and you can see that it starts off and initially it makes mistakes,
你可以看到它一开始就会犯错误，
but eventually it learns how to, how to take the turns at high speeds,
但最终它会学会如何在高速下转弯，
and interestingly you can do, you can take this idea
有趣的是，你可以采用这个想法，
and you can run it in parallel,
你可以并行运行它，
so you can take thousands of cars
所以你可以使用数千辆汽车，
and you can, you can put them on the same track
你可以把它们放在同一条轨道上，
and in the beginning they all make mistakes,
一开始他们都会犯错误，
but eventually they get the solution right
但最终他们得到了正确的解决方案，
and eventually that [joint] policy ends up being the policy that reliably controls the the vehicles,
最终[联合]策略最终成为了可靠地控制车辆的策略，
so, it's very, it's really a very exciting area,
所以，它确实是一个非常令人兴奋的领域，
reinforcement learning, much like deep learning, has been invented decades ago,
强化学习，像深度学习一样，在几十年前就发明出来了，
but it works well now,
但是它现在运行得很好，
because of the advent of, of computation,
因为有了计算的出现，
we have so much more computes today, than we had 40 years ago,
我们今天拥有的计算比 40 年前要多得多，
we have so much more data for deep neural networks today than we had 40 years ago,
我们今天拥有的深度神经网络数据比 40 年前多得多，
and so these techniques that did not do so well back then,
所以，这些当时做得不是很好的技术，
all of a sudden are creating extraordinary possibilities and capabilities in our agents.
突然之间为我们的代理创造了非凡的可能性和能力。
Now this is a simple simulation,
这是一个简单的模拟，
in order to get the simulation to drive a real robot,
为了让模拟驱动一个真正的机器人，
we actually need to think about,
我们实际上需要考虑，
the dynamics of the robot,
机器人的动力学，
and so in other words,
换句话说，
we have to take into account what the vehicle looks like,
我们必须考虑到车辆的样子，
what are its kinematics, what are its dynamics,
它的运动学是什么，它的动力学是什么，
and so here is a vehicle that is running the policy learned in simulation,
所以，这是一辆运行在模拟中学到的策略的车辆，
so it's really cool,
所以这真的很酷，
because really we are now able to train in simulation,
因为我们现在能够进行模拟训练，
and if the model that we have for the vehicle dynamics is good enough,
如果我们拥有的车辆动力学模型足够好，
we can take the policy that was learned very fast in simulation
我们可以采用在模拟中非常快地学习到的策略，
and we can deploy it on the vehicle,
我们可以将其部署在车辆上，
and here are two vehicles racing with each other,
这是两辆车，互相比赛，
the white car and the green car,
白色的和绿色的，
so check out what the white car is doing,
所以看看那辆白色的车在做什么，
see how it snuck,
看看它是怎么偷偷溜过去的，
wow, it's really great,
哇，真的很棒，
I wish I could race like this,
我希望我能像这样比赛，
so this is really, really exciting,
所以这真的非常令人兴奋，
now in this case, the vehicles have limited field of view
在这种情况下，车辆的视野有限，
and they get the position of the other vehicles on the track,
而且它们获得赛道上其他车辆的位置，
but only only, so they get this position from an external localization system,
它们从外部定位系统获得这个位置，
but they only know where the the vehicles within their field of view are,
但它们只知道它们视野内的车辆在哪里，
so look at this, that's great.
所以，看看这个，太棒了。
So okay, so what can we do with with these methodologies,
那么，好的，我们可以用这些方法做什么，
so we've seen how we can use deep learning to understand
所以，我们已经看到了如何使用深度学习来理解
the the view of the vehicle from cameras,
从摄像机中看到的车辆，
we've seen an example of learning to steer,
我们已经看到了一个学习驾驶的例子，
what can we do.
我们能做些什么。
Well, I think that these, these advancements in robotics
我认为这些机器人技术的进步，
are really enabling the possibility that you saw in the first slide,
确实使你在第一张幻灯片中看到成为可能，
the possibility of creating many robots that can do many tasks
创造出可以完成许多任务的许多机器人的可能性，
and much more complicated tasks than what we see here.
而且比我们这里看到的任务复杂得多。
And so what I want to talk about next is the autopilot,
所以我接下来想要谈的是自动驾驶，
how do we take these pieces together to enable the autopilot,
我们如何把这些部分放在一起来启用自动驾驶，
meaning to enable a self driving vehicle,
也就是启用自动驾驶汽车，
I don't mean so,
我不是这个意思，
this autopilot is not the Tesla,
这个自动驾驶不是特斯拉，
autopilot, It's just the idea that you have a full self driving vehicle,
自动驾驶，这只是一个想法，你有一辆完整的自动驾驶汽车，
now, in order to do this,
现在，为了做到这一点，
we need to advance the brain more,
我们需要更多地推动大脑的发展，
we need to do more about the learning, reasoning and planning part of the car.
我们需要在汽车的学习、推理和规划方面做更多的工作。
So let me, let me ask you,
所以让我问你，
do you know when was the first autonomous coast to coast drive in the United States,
你知道美国第一辆自动驾驶的海岸到海岸是什么时候，
any guesses?
有没有人猜到？
Not you, I know, you know.
不是你，我知道你知道的。
2000 interesting.
2000 年，有意思。
Actually, it was in 1995,
实际上，那是在 1995 年，
in 1995, a Carnegie Mellon project called Navlab,
在 1995 年，卡内基梅隆大学的一个项目叫 Navlab ，
built a car that that actually was was driven by a machine learning engine called Alvinn,
制造了一辆实际上是由机器学习引擎 Alvinn 驱动的汽车，
and Alvinn drove this car all the way from Washington DC to Los Angeles,
Alvinn 开着这辆车从华盛顿特区一路开到洛杉矶，
and the car was in autonomous mode for a large part of the highway driving,
在高速公路上的大部分时间里，这辆车都处于自动驾驶模式，
but there was always a student there ready to to take control
但总有一个学生准备好控制汽车，
and the car did not, did not drive in autonomous mode,
汽车有时不在自动驾驶模式下驾驶，
when there were, when it was raining or when there was a lot of congestion or when the car had to had to take exits,
当有雨、拥堵或汽车不得不离开出口时，
so this is what the car did,
这就是这辆车做的事情，
it went from Washington DC, all the way to Los Angeles,
它从华盛顿特区一直到洛杉矶，
now 1995 is a long time ago, right,
现在 1995 年是很久以前的事了，
I mean, it's before many of you were born.
我是说，那是在你们很多人出生之前，
So it's really extraordinary to think about,
所以，特别需要思考，
what is needed in terms of advancement, in terms of progress
需要哪些方面的进步，
in order to get from where we were back then to the point,
才能从我们回到当时的位置，
where we can actually see deployed autonomous vehicles,
我们可以真正看到部署的自动驾驶汽车，
and by the way,
顺便说一句，
you should come and check out the MIT autonomous vehicles,
你应该来看看 MIT 的自动驾驶汽车，
which Alexander has built over the past five years,
是由 Alexander 在过去五年里制造的，
which are very powerful and can drive in our neighborhood,
它们非常强大，可以在我们附近驾驶，
and we'll talk about how they drive.
我们将讨论他们是如何驾驶的。
But interestingly, this was not the first time when we had cars racing in autonomous modes on, on highways,
但有趣的是，这并不是我们第一次在高速公路上以自动驾驶模式驾驶汽车，
in fact, do you know when was the first autonomous highway drive in the world, anywhere in the world,
事实上，你知道世界上任何地方第一次自动驾驶高速公路是什么时候吗，
so it was in 1986,
它是在 1986 年，
and in 1986, German engineer Ernst Dickmann started thinking about,
在 1986 年，德国工程师 Ernst Dickmann 开始考虑，
how he could turn his Van into an autonomous vehicle,
如何将他的面包车变成一辆自动驾驶汽车，
and so he put computers and cameras on the Van
所以，他在货车上安装了电脑和摄像头，
and began running tests on an empty section of the German autobahn,
并开始在德国高速公路的一个空的部分进行测试，
which had not been open for for public driving,
那里还没有对公共驾驶开放，
and he was able to actually get his Van to drive on that empty road,
他能够让他的货车在那条空的道路上行驶，
but interestingly, when he started developing this work,
但有趣的是，当他开始开发这项工作时，
computers needed about 10 minutes to analyze an image,
计算机大约需要 10 分钟来分析一幅图像，
okay, can you imagine,
好的，你能想象吗，
okay, so how do you, how do you go from that
好的，那么你如何从这个，
to enabling an autonomous vehicle to drive at 90 kilometers an hour,
使自动驾驶汽车能够以每小时 90 公里的速度行驶，
well, what they did was,
他们所做的就是，
they, they, they developed some very fast solutions
他们开发了一些非常快速的解决方案，
for paring down the image to only the aspects that they needed to look at
把图像缩小到只需要看他们需要看的方面，
and they assumed that there were no obstacles in the world,
他们假设世界上没有障碍，
which made the problem much easier,
这使得问题变得容易得多，
because all the car had to do was to stay on on the road,
因为汽车所要做的就是保持在路上，
so it's really super interesting to think about how visual processing improved
所以，思考视觉处理如何提高是非常有趣的，
from one frame per ten minutes to a hundred frames per second,
从每十分钟一帧提高到每秒一百帧，
and this has been a game changer for autonomous cars,
这已经改变了自动驾驶汽车的游戏规则，
and we're getting back to the connection between hardware and software,
我们又回到了硬件和软件之间的联系，
we need both in order to get good solutions for real problems.
我们两者都需要，才能为实际问题找到好的解决方案。
The other thing that happened in autonomous driving was that the lidar sensors,
自动驾驶中发生的另一件事是激光雷达传感器，
decreased the uncertainty and increased safety.
减少了不确定性，增加了安全性。
And today we have many companies and groups that are deploying self driving cars,
今天，我们有许多公司和组织正在部署自动驾驶汽车，
this is an example from Singapore,
这是一个来自新加坡的例子，
it's, it's a vehicle we deployed
这是我们部署的车辆，
and in fact, we had the public ride our vehicle in 2014,
事实上，我们在 2014 年让公众乘坐我们的车辆，
we have vehicles at MIT,
我们在 MIT 有车，
we have a lot of other groups that are developing these vehicles,
我们还有很多其他的团队开发这些车辆，
now, before we had lidar, we had sonar
在我们有激光雷达之前，我们有声纳，
and nothing worked when we had sonar,
当我们有声纳的时候，什么都不能用，
because, when you, when you work with sonar,
因为，当你使用声纳时，
the sonar beams just kind of go forward and then they bounce,
声纳波束只是向前移动，然后它们就会反弹，
and if the angle is about plus minus seven degrees,
如果角度大约是正负 7 度，
you will hear the ping back,
你会听到 ping 回来，
but if the angle, so if the sonar bounces on a surface,
但是如果角度，所以如果声纳在一个平面，
that's more than seven degrees angled from from the direction of the sonar,
与声纳方向成七度角以上，
that sonar ping will bounce off
那个声纳 ping 就会反弹，
and it will bounce on other objects and walls
它会反弹到另一个物体和墙壁，
and you will get wrong direction measurements, wrong distance measurements.
你会得到方向测量错误，距离测量错误。
So with lidar, that problem went away,
有了激光雷达，这个问题就消失了，
so all of a sudden, a powerful, accurate sensor made a huge difference,
突然之间，一个强大、准确的传感器产生了巨大的变化，
all the algorithms that were developed on sonar and didn't work started working,
所有在声纳上开发的、不起作用的算法都开始工作，
when the lidar was introduced,
当激光雷达被引入时，
it was really exciting.
这真的很令人兴奋。
Okay, now when we think about autonomous driving,
好的，现在，当我们思考自动驾驶，
there are several key parameters that emerge,
会出现几个关键参数，
as we think about what the capabilities of these systems are,
当我们思考这些系统的能力时，
and one, one question is,
有一个问题是，
how complex is the environment where the car is moving,
汽车行驶的环境有多复杂，
if it's an empty road like in the German case,
如果像德国的情况一样，这是一条空路，
then the problem is much easier,
那么问题就容易多了，
then we have to ask ourselves,
然后我们必须问自己，
how, how complex are the interactions between the car and the environment,
汽车和环境之间的相互作用有多复杂，
and we also have to think about,
我们还必须考虑，
how complex is the reasoning of the car,
汽车的推理有多复杂，
how fast is the car going,
汽车开得有多快，
and underlying all these questions is a fundamental question,
所有这些问题背后都有一个根本性的问题，
and this fundamental question is,
而这个根本性的问题是，
how does the car cope with uncertainties,
汽车如何应对不确定性，
now you have seen that,
现在你已经看到，
machine learning has uncertainty associated with it,
机器学习具有与之相关的不确定性，
so as you consider deploying machine learning on safety critical applications,
所以，当你考虑在安全关键型应用程序上部署机器学习时，
it is super important
这是极其重要的，
to consider the connection between between your context, the uncertainties of the models that you're deploying and what the actual application requires.
考虑你的环境、你要部署的模型的不确定性和实际应用程序需求之间的联系。
And I will tell you,
我要告诉你，
that today we have very effective and deployable solutions for robot cars
今天我们有非常有效和可部署的机器人汽车解决方案，
that move safely in easy environments,
可以在简单的环境中安全移动，
where there aren't many static nor moving obstacles,
那里没有太多静态或移动的障碍物，
and you can, you can see from this example,
你可以从这个例子中看到，
this is, this is an example of the MIT car
这是一个 MIT 汽车的例子，
and its you can see this,
你可以看到，
this car operating autonomously without any issues at Fort Devens,
这辆车在 Fort Devens 自动驾驶，没有任何问题，
where there aren't too many obstacles,
那里没有太多障碍，
and the car is perfectly capable of avoiding the obstacle,
这辆车完全有能力避开障碍物，
by the way, that's my car,
顺便说一下，那是我的车，
so I'm very glad that the car is very capable of avoiding obstacles,
所以我很高兴这辆车能够很好地避开障碍物，
and in fact, I was so convinced,
事实上，我非常确信，
I said, okay, we can use my car as the obstacle.
我说，好的，我们可以用我的车作为障碍。
But the sensors don't work well in weather,
但是传感器在天气中不能很好地工作，
and the uncertainty of the perception system increases significantly if it rains hard or it snows,
如果下大雨或下雪，感知系统的不确定性会显著增加，
and the uncertainty of the vehicle prior also increases,
而车辆先验的不确定性也增加了，
in the case of extreme congestion,
在极端拥堵的情况下，
where you have erratic driving with vehicles,
车辆行驶不稳定，
with people with scooters,
人们骑着踏板车，
even with cows on the road,
甚至路上还有牛，
and this is a video I took during a taxi ride in Bangalore,
这是我在班加罗尔打车时拍摄的一段视频，
there come the cows.
牛来了。
So, there are so many important preconditions,
所以，有这么多重要的前提条件，
and many of these preconditions revolve around uncertainty in perception, planning, learning, reasoning and execution,
其中许多前提条件围绕着感知、规划、学习、推理和执行方面的不确定性，
before we can get to RoboTaxi,
然后我们进入 RoboTaxi 之前，
we can have many other robot solutions,
我们可以有许多其他的机器人解决方案，
that are much, that can happen today,
这些解决方案在今天可以发生，
and so I want to tell you,
所以我想告诉你，
that many companies and research teams are deploying and developing self driving cars
许多公司和研究团队正在部署和开发自动驾驶汽车，
and many of them follow a very simple solution,
其中许多公司遵循一个非常简单的解决方案，
which you can adopt and turn your car into a self driving car,
你可以采用这个解决方案，将你的汽车变成自动驾驶汽车，
so here's what you have to do,
所以这就是你要做的，
you take your car, you extend it to drive by wires,
你拿着你的车，你把它扩展到有线驾驶，
so that your computer can talk to to the steering and the acceleration, the throttle controls,
这样你的计算机就可以与方向盘、加速和油门控制进行交互，
so then you further extend this car with sensors,
然后，你进一步扩展这辆车的传感器，
and most of the sensors we use are cameras and lidars,
我们使用的大多数传感器是摄像头和激光雷达，
and then there are a suite of software models, modules,
然后是一套软件模块，
and this includes a perception module,
其中包括一个感知模块，
that provides support for making maps and for detecting a static and dynamic obstacles,
它为绘制地图和检测静态和动态障碍物提供支持，
and then we have an estimation module,
然后我们有一个评估模块，
that identifies where the robot is located,
来识别机器人的位置，
and it does so by comparing what what the perception system sees now against a map that was created by looking at the infrastructure,
它通过将感知系统现在看到的东西与通过查看基础设施创建的地图进行比较来做到这一点，
and finally, there is a learning planning and control system
最后，还有一个学习计划和控制系统，
that figures out what the car should do based on where it is,
它可以根据汽车所在的位置计算出它应该做什么，
so this is it, this is the recipe,
所以就是这样，这是清单，
you can take your vehicle and turn it into an autonomous vehicle,
你可以把你的车变成一辆自动驾驶汽车，
and as you do so,
当你这样做的时候，
you really have to think about foundationally,
你真的必须从根本上考虑，
what are the computational units that you have to make, you have to create,
你必须制作的计算单元是什么，
so you have to process the sensor data,
所以你必须处理传感器数据，
you have to detect obstacles,
你必须检测障碍物，
you have to localize the vehicle,
你必须定位车辆，
you have to plan,
你必须规划，
and then you have to move.
然后你必须移动。
And so there are so many works that address each of these sub tasks that are involved in autonomous navigation,
有如此多的工作来解决涉及到自主导航的每一个子任务，
and, and some of these works are model based,
其中一些工作是基于模型的，
and some of the works are machine learning based,
一些工作是基于机器学习的，
but what's really interesting is that,
但真正有趣的是，
in this autonomous driving pipeline, the classical autonomous driving pipeline,
在这条自动驾驶管道中，经典的自动驾驶管道，
there are a lot of parameters,
有很多参数，
so for every solution of each of these individual problems,
所以对于这些单个问题的每一个解决方案，
you have to hand engineer parameters for any type of road situation that the car will encounter,
你必须为汽车将遇到的任何类型的道路情况向工程师提供参数，
and then you will have to think about how the modules get stitched together,
然后，你将不得不考虑如何将模块缝合在一起，
you need to define parameters that connect the modules together,
你需要定义将模块连接在一起的参数，
and this is very tough to do in a robust way,
这很难用一种很健壮的方式来实现，
and it brings brittleness to these solutions,
它给这些解决方案带来了脆弱性，
in, in fact, you have to really think about, what are the parameters,
事实上，你必须考虑这些参数是什么，
if you have nighttime driving
如果你在夜间开车，
or if you have rainy weather
或者下雨的天气，
or you're, you're in the country, on a country road
或者你在乡下的乡间道路上，
or in the city on a city road,
或者在城市的道路上，
or you're on the road with no lane markings,
或者你在没有车道标志的道路上，
so these are really challenging things,
所以，这些都是具有挑战性的事情，
that the first solutions for autonomous driving had to reason through.
自动驾驶的第一个解决方案必须处理的。
Now, in Alexander's PhD thesis,
现在，在 Alexander 的博士论文中，
his idea was to utilize a large dataset
他的想法是利用大型数据集，
to learn a representation of what humans did in similar situations
来了解人类在类似情况下的表现，
and develop autonomous driving solutions,
并开发自动驾驶解决方案，
that drive more like humans than than the the traditional pipeline,
驾驶起来比传统管道更像人类，
which is much more roboticy if you, if you like.
如果你愿意的话，传统管道更像机器人。
So then the question is,
那么接下来的问题是，
how can we use machine learning to go directly from sensors to actuation,
我们如何使用机器学习来直接从传感器到执行机构，
in other words, can we compress all the stuff in the middle
换句话说，我们能压缩中间的所有东西，
and use learning to connect directly perception and action.
并用学习将感知和行动直接联系起来。
So the solutions that we employed
所以，我们采用的解决方案，
build on things we have already talked about,
建立在我们已经讨论过的东西之上，
we can use deep learning and reinforcement learning
我们可以使用深度学习和强化学习，
to take us from images of roads onto steering and throttle on what to do,
将我们从道路的图像带到转向和油门上，决定要做什么，
so this is really great,
所以这真的很棒，
because you can train on certain kinds of roads,
因为你可以在某些类型的道路上训练，
and, and you can then take your vehicle and put the vehicle in completely different driving environments and driving situations,
然后，你可以把你的车放在完全不同的驾驶环境和驾驶情况下。
and you don't need new parameters,
你不需要新的参数，
you don't need retraining，
你不需要再训练，
you can go exactly directly to what the car has to do.
你可以直接直接去做汽车必须做的事情。
So in other words, we can learn a model
换句话说，我们可以学习一种模型，
to go from raw perception,
从原始的感知出发，
and here you can think of this as pixels from a camera,
在这里，你可以把它想象成来自相机的像素，
and the other thing we feed the vehicle is noisy street view maps,
我们给车提供的另一样东西是嘈杂的街景地图，
so these are not the high definition maps,
这些地图并不是高清地图，
that are usually created by autonomous driving labs and companies.
通常由自动驾驶实验室和公司制作。
And so you can do this
所以你可以这样做，
to directly infer a full continuous probability distribution over the space of all control,
直接推断出在所有控制空间上的完全连续的概率分布，
and here the red lines indicate the inferred trajectories of the vehicle projected out onto the image frame,
这里的红线表示投射到图像框上的车辆的推断轨迹，
and the opacity represents the learned density function by our model,
不透明度用我们的模型表示学习到的密度函数，
and so this is done by training a deep learning model,
这是通过训练深度学习模型来完成的，
and the deep learning model can output the parameters of this conditional distribution directly from human driving data.
并且深度学习模型可以直接从人类驾驶数据输出该条件分布的参数。
Okay, so more precisely,
好的，更准确地说，
the input to our learning system consists of camera feeds from three cameras,
我们学习系统的输入包括三个摄像头，
camera that looks forward and two cameras that look sideways,
前视摄像头和两个侧视摄像头，
and also the street view maps,
还有街景地图，
and from this, from this data, this data is processed,
而且从这个数据进行处理，
and it's, from this data,
从这些数据中，
we can learn to maximize the likelihood of particular control signals for particular situations,
我们可以学习最大限度地提高特定情况下特定控制信号的可能性，
and amazingly, the solution also allows us to localize the vehicle,
令人惊讶的是，这个解决方案还允许我们对车辆进行本地化，
so it's really super exciting.
所以这真的是非常令人兴奋。
Okay, so we can, we can, we can get this human like control,
好的，所以我们可以像人类一样控制，
but this human like control requires a lot of data,
但这种像人类一样的控制需要大量的数据，
and I've told you at the beginning,
我在一开始就告诉过你们，
that we have to be careful with the data,
我们必须小心处理数据，
because there are a lot of corner cases,
因为有很多边界条件，
there are a lot of typical near accident situations,
有很多典型的近事故情况，
for which it's difficult to generate real data.
很难产生真实的数据。
So, for instance,
所以，举个例子，
let's see,
让我们看看，
for instance, if you have,
例如，如果你有，
if you want to ensure that the car will not be responsible for an accident
如果你想确保汽车不会对事故负责，
and will know what to do when it comes to road situations like this,
并且在遇到这样的道路情况时，知道该怎么做，
it would be pretty expensive
这将是相当昂贵的，
to take a car and crash that car in order to generate the data.
开一辆车撞毁那辆车，来生成数据。
So instead, what we do is,
所以，我们所做的是，
we do the training in simulation,
我们在模拟中进行训练，
and so Alexander developed the vista simulator,
所以 Alexander 开发了 Vista 模拟器，
and the Vista simulator can model multiple agents, multiple types of sensors
Vista 模拟器可以对多个代理、多种类型的传感器，
and multiple types of agent to agent interaction,
以及多种类型的代理之间的交互进行建模，
and, and so the Vista simulator has been recently open sourced,
Vista 模拟器最近是开源的，
you can get the code from vista.csail.mit.edu,
你可以从 vista.csail.mit.edu 获得代码，
and a lot of people are already using the system.
而且很多人已经在使用这个系统了。
So what we get from Vista,
所以我们从 Vista 得到什么，
is the ability to simulate different physical sensing modalities,
是模拟不同物理感应模式的能力，
that means including 2D cameras, 3D LiDAR, event cameras and, and so forth,
这意味着包括 2D 摄像机， 3D 激光雷达，活动摄像机等等，
and then you get the possibility to, to simulate different types of environmental, situations and perturbations,
然后你有可能模拟不同类型的环境，情况和扰动，
you can simulate weather, you can simulate different lighting,
你可以模拟天气，你可以模拟不同的照明，
you can simulate, simulate different types of roads
你可以模拟不同类型的道路，
and you can also simulate different types of of interactions.
你还可以模拟不同类型的互动。
So here's how we use Vista,
下面是我们使用 Vista 的方法，
we can take one high quality dataset,
我们可以获取一个高质量的数据集，
taken from a human driven vehicle,
从人类驾驶的车辆上，
We can take this very high definition dataset
我们可以利用这个非常高清晰度的数据集，
and then in simulation, we can turn it into anything we want,
然后在模拟中，我们可以把它变成我们想要的任何东西，
we can turn it into erratic driving,
我们可以把它变成不稳定的驾驶，
we can turn it into near accident simulation, situation,
我们可以把它变成接近事故的情况，
we can turn it into anything, anything you want,
我们可以把它变成任何你想要的东西，
so for instance, here you can see our original data
例如，你可以在这里看到我们的原始数据，
and you can see how this original data can be mapped in simulation
你可以看到如何在模拟中映射原始数据，
and in a way that looks very realistically into a new simulated trajectory,
并以一种非常逼真的方式映射到新的模拟轨迹中，
that is erratic
这个轨迹是不稳定的，
and that now exists as part of our training set in Vista.
现在作为我们 Vista 中训练集的一部分存在。
And so we can, we can do this,
所以我们可以这样做，
we can use this data
我们可以使用这些数据，
and then we can learn a policy,
然后我们可以学习一项策略，
we can evaluate this policy offline
我们可以离线评估这一策略，
and ultimately deploy it on the vehicle.
并最终将其部署在车辆上。
And this works by first updating the state of all agents,
这是通过首先更新所有代理的状态，
based on the vehicle dynamics and interactions,
根据车辆动力学和相互作用，
and then by recreating the world from the new viewpoints of the agents,
然后从代理的新视角重建世界，
once you move them,
一旦你移动它们，
the world will look different to the agent than in the original driving dataset.
在代理看来，世界将与原始驾驶数据集中不同。
And finally we can,
最后，我们可以，
we can then render the image from the different agents viewpoints
然后我们可以从不同的代理视角渲染图像，
and we can perform the control.
我们可以执行控制。
So, so this is really cool,
所以，这真的很酷，
there are several other simulation engines
还有其他几个模拟引擎，
and there are simulation engines,
有一些模拟引擎，
that rely on on Imitation Learning or on Domain Randomization or there is CARLA,
依赖于 Imitation Learning 或 Domain Randomization 或 CARLA ，
that's very effective, that seem to real,
它非常有效，看起来是真实的，
however, our solution works better than all the other solutions
然而，我们的解决方案比所有其他解决方案工作得更好，
and here you can see the results of comparing,
在这里你可以看到比较的结果，
what happens in Vista with the, with what happens in the existing simulators in the state of the art.
Vista 中发生的情况与现有模拟器中最先进的情况。
So the top line shows crash locations in red
所以，上面的线以红色显示撞车地点，
and the bottom line shows mean trajectory variation in color,
下面的线以颜色显示平均轨迹变化，
and you can, you can see that our solution really does the best,
你可以看到我们的解决方案确实做得最好，
and in fact, the solution is able to do things that other simulation based learning, based control cannot do,
事实上，这个解决方案能够做其他基于控制学习的模拟不能做的事情，
for instance, in our solution,
例如，在我们的解决方案中，
we are able to recover from orientations that point the vehicle off the road,
我们能够从指向车辆离开道路的方向恢复，
or we are able to to recover from being in the wrong in the wrong lane.
或者我们能够从错误的车道中恢复。
So here's a vehicle that is executing the learning base control,
这是一辆执行基于控制学习的车辆，
and here's Alexander with his vehicle,
这是 Alexander 和他的车辆，
that was trained using data from urban driving,
这辆车是用城市驾驶的数据训练的，
and now he's driving to the soccer field,
现在他正开车去足球场，
and you can see that,
你可以看到，
he, he's able to drive to, to get this car, to drive him to the soccer field
他能够开这辆车，让车送他去足球场，
without doing any training,
不需要做任何训练，
without ever having seen this road
也不需要看过这条路，
and explicitly providing data about this road,
也不需要明确提供这条路的数据，
so this is pretty cool, right.
所以这很酷，对吧。
All right, so, okay, I'm going to open the hood for you,
好的，所以，好的，我要为你打开[引擎盖]，
and so I'm going to show you what happens inside the decision engine of this solution,
我将向你展示此解决方案的决策引擎内部发生了什么，
so let me orient you in this image,
所以，让我在这张图片中为你定位，
bottom right, you see the map of the environment,
右下角，你可以看到环境地图，
top left, you see the camera input stream,
左上角，你看到摄像头输入流，
bottom left, you see the attention map of the vehicle,
左下角，你看到车辆的注意力图，
and then in the middle you see the decision engine,
然后在中间，你可以看到决策引擎，
the decision engine has about 100,000 neurons and about half a million parameters.
决策引擎有大约 10 万个神经元和大约 50 万个参数。
And I will challenge you to to figure out,
我会向你挑战弄清楚，
if there are any patterns that associate the state of neurons with the behavior of the vehicle,
是否有任何模式将神经元的状态与车辆的行为联系起来，
it's really hard to see,
真的很难看到，
because there are so many of them,
因为有太多这样的模式，
there's just so much stuff that is happening in parallel at the same time.
在同一时间，有太多的事情同时发生。
And then have a look at the attention map,
然后看一下注意力图，
so it turns out this vehicle is looking at the bushes on the roads
这辆车是在看着道路上的灌木丛，
in order on the road in order to make decisions,
以便在道路上做出决定，
still, it seems to do a pretty good job,
尽管如此，它似乎做得相当好，
but we asked ourselves,
但我们问自己，
can we do better,
我们能做得更好吗，
can we have more reliable learning based solutions.
我们能有更可靠的基于学习的解决方案。
And so yesterday Ramin introduced liquid networks and introduced neural circuit policies,
昨天 Ramin 介绍了液态网络，并介绍了神经回路策略，
and so I just want to drill down a little bit more into this area,
所以我只想深入到这个领域，
because you can now compare,
因为你现在可以比较，
you can now understand how the the original engine worked,
你现在可以理解最初的引擎是如何工作的，
and you can compare that against what we get from liquid networks.
你可以把它与我们从液态网络中获得的进行比较。
And so look at this, we have nineteen neurons,
看看这个，我们有 19 个神经元，
and now it's much easier to look at patterns of activation of these neurons
现在很容易看到这些神经元的激活模式，
and associate them with the behavior of the vehicle,
并将它们与车辆的行为联系起来，
and the attention map is so much cleaner, right,
注意力地图也干净多了，
the vehicle is looking at the road horizon and at the sides of the road,
车辆看着道路地平线和道路两边，
which is what we all do when we drive a vehicle.
这是我们开车时都会做的事情。
Now remember how, so remember that Ramin told us that,
记得， Ramin 告诉我们，
this this model called liquid time-constant network,
这个模型叫做液态时间常数网络，
is a continuous time network,
是一个连续的时间网络，
this model changes what the neuron computes
这个模型改变了神经元计算的内容，
and in particular we start with a well behaved state space model
特别是我们从行为良好的状态空间模型开始，
to increase the neuron stability during learning,
以增加神经元在学习过程中的稳定性，
and then we have nonlinearities over the synaptic inputs
然后，我们对突触输入进行非线性处理，
to increase the expressivity of the model
以增加模型的表现力，
and to also increase the model state during training and inference,
并在训练和推理过程中增加模型状态，
and by plugging these equations into each other,
通过将这些方程相互插入，
we can see the equation of the LTC neuron,
我们可以看到 LTC 神经元的方程，
where here the function is,
这里的函数，
where the function here determines not only the state of the neuron,
这里的函数，不仅决定神经元的状态，
but also this function can be is controlled by new input at the time of execution of inference,
而且这个函数还可以在执行推理时由新的输入来控制，
so what's really cool about this model is that,
所以，这个模型真正酷的地方在于，
it is able to dynamically adapt after training based on the inputs that it sees,
它能够在训练后根据它看到的输入动态适应，
and this is something very powerful about liquid networks.
这是液态网络的一个非常强大的东西。
Now, in addition to changing the neuron equation,
现在，除了改变神经元方程，
we also change the wiring
我们还改变了连线，
and this new type of wiring,
这种新型的连线，
essentially gives function to the neurons in a deep neural network,
本质上将函数给了深层神经网络中的神经元，
every neurons is the same,
每个神经元都是一样的，
in our architecture,
在我们的体系结构中，
we have input neurons,
我们有输入神经元，
we have we have control neurons,
我们有控制神经元，
we have inter neurons
我们有中间神经元，
and they each do different things.
它们各自做不同的事情。
And so with this in mind,
考虑到这一点，
we can look again at the beautiful solution that is enabled by liquid networks,
我们可以再次看看由液态网络实现的漂亮的解决方案，
and the solution keeps the car on on the roads
这个解决方案让汽车保持在道路上行驶，
and only requires 19 neurons to deliver that kind of function.
只需要 19 个神经元就能实现这种功能。
And you can see here,
你可以在这里看到，
that the attention of the solution is extremely focused
解决方案的注意力非常集中，
as compared to other models,
与其他模型相比，
like CNN or CT-RNN or LSTM,
比如 CNN 或 CT-RNN 或 LSTM ，
which are much more noisy.
它们的噪音要大得多。
So I hope you now have a better understanding of how liquid networks work
所以，我希望你们现在能更好地理解流动网络是如何工作的，
and what their properties are,
以及它们的特性是什么，
now we can take this model and apply it to many other problems.
现在我们可以把这个模型应用到许多其他问题上。
So here's a problem we call Kenyon Run,
所以这是一个我们称为 Kenyon Run 的问题，
where we have taken a liquid network
我们采用了液态网络，
and we have implemented it On a task of flying a plane
并在一个飞行的飞机上实施了它，
with one degree of freedom,
只有一个自由度，
where the plane can only go up and down,
飞机只能上下移动，
but it has to hit these obstacles,
但它必须撞到这些障碍物，
which are at locations that the plane does not know
这些障碍物位于飞机不知道的位置，
and the plane also does not know what the environment looks like,
飞机也不知道环境是什么样子的，
and so in particular when you have,
所以特别是当你有，
we have when, when you have the, when you implement the task with one degree of freedom control for the plane,
当你用一个自由度控制飞机执行任务时，
all you need is eleven liquid neurons,
你所需要的只是 11 个液态神经元，
if you want to control all the degrees of freedom of the plane,
如果你想控制飞机的所有自由度，
then you need 24 neurons,
那么你需要 24 个神经元，
It's still much smaller than the huge models that we're talking about today.
它仍然比我们今天谈论的巨大模型小得多。
Here's another task, we call Drone Dodgeball,
这是另一项任务，我们称之为无人机躲避球，
where the objective is to keep a drone at specified location
目标是让无人机保持在指定的位置，
and the drone has to protect itself, when when balls come its way
无人机必须保护自己，当球飞过来的时候，
and you can see a two degree of freedom solution to Drone Dodgeball
你可以看到无人机躲避球的两个自由度的解决方案，
and that's the network,
这就是网络，
you can see how it, how all the neurons fire
你可以看到它是如何激发所有神经元的，
and you can really associate the the function of
你可以真正将函数联系起来，
of this controller of this learning based control with activation patterns of the neurons,
这种基于学习的控制与神经元的激活模式联系起来，
and so very excited,
这非常令人兴奋，
because in fact, we're able to extract decision trees from these kinds of solutions,
因为，事实上，我们能够从这些类型的解决方案中提取决策树，
and these decision trees provide human understandable, human, understandable explanations,
这些决策树提供了人类可以理解的解释，
and so this is really important for safety critical systems.
这对安全关键系统来说非常重要。
All right, so let's see,
好的，我们来看看，
Ramin told you that,
Ramin 告诉你们，
these liquid networks are dynamic causal models
这些液态网络是动态因果模型，
and I want to show you some more examples,
我想给你们展示更多的例子，
that, that explain how these models are dynamic causal models.
解释这些模型如何是动态因果模型。
So here you can see the,
所以在这里你可以看到，
so, so here we're studying the task
所以我们在这里研究的任务是，
of finding an object inside a wooded environment
在树木繁茂的环境中寻找物体，
and the object, and here here are some examples of the data
这里有一些数据的例子，
that we have used to train this task,
我们用来这项任务，
so essentially, we've had a human pilot drive a drone to, to, to accomplish the task.
从本质上说，我们让一名飞行员驾驶无人机来完成这项任务。
Now, this is the data,
现在，这就是数据，
so check this out,
来看看这个，
we have then used a standard deep neural network
然后我们使用了一个标准的深度神经网络，
and we have asked this network to solve this problem,
我们要求这个网络来解决这个问题，
and the attention map of the network is really all over the place,
而且网络的关注点地图无处不在，
you can see that the network, the deep neural network solution, is very confused,
你可以看到深度神经网络的解决方案非常混乱，
but check out something else,
但看看其他的东西，
the data that we collected was summertime data,
我们收集的数据是夏季数据，
and now it's Fall,
而现在是秋天，
so the background is no longer green,
所以，背景不再是绿色的，
we have, we don't have as many leaves on trees
我们没有那么多树上的叶子，
and so the context for this task has completely changed.
所以这项任务的背景完全改变了。
By comparison, the the liquid network is able to focus on the task,
相比之下，液态网络能够专注于任务，
is not confused
不会感到困惑，
and is able to go directly to the object that it needs to find,
能够直接到达它需要找到的对象，
and look how clean the attention map of this of this example is,
看看这个例子的注意力图是多么清晰，
so this is very exciting,
所以这是非常令人兴奋的，
because it, it really shows that,
因为它真的表明，
with liquid networks,
对于液态网络，
we have a solution,
我们有一个解决方案，
that is, that is able to in some sense abstract out the context of training
在某种意义上能够抽象出训练的背景，
and that means we can get zero shot transfers from one environment to another.
这意味着我们可以从一个环境到另一个环境进行零训练转移。
And so moreover, we actually have done the same task in the middle of the Winter,
此外，我们在冬季也做了同样的工作，
when we no longer have leaves,
那时我们不再有树叶了，
we have black tree lines,
我们有黑色的树干，
and the environment looks much, much different than the environment where we trained,
环境看起来与我们训练的环境有很大不同，
and this kind of this kind of ability to transfer from one set of training data to completely different environments
这种从一组训练数据转移到完全不同环境的能力，
is truly transformational for the capabilities of machine learning.
对于机器学习的能力来说是真正的变革性。
Well, we've done more than that,
嗯，我们做的还不止这些，
so we've taken our train solution
所以我们采用了我们的系列解决方案，
and we deployed it in the lab,
并在实验室中进行了部署，
so here is, here is Markram,
这是 Markram ，
who worked on this problem
他致力于解决这个问题，
and he is,
他是，
and and look at the attention map,
然后看一下注意力图，
I mean, he, the environment is not not even the woods,
我的意思是，他的环境甚至不是树林，
it's, it's an office,
这是一间办公室，
it's an indoor environment.
这是一个室内环境。
And we see other examples,
我们看到其他例子，
where we take our solution
我们使用我们的解决方案，
and we deploy it to find the same object, the chair,
我们部署它来寻找相同的对象，那把椅子，
just outside of this data building
就在这个数据大楼外面，
and this is the the deep neural network solution,
这是深度神经网络解决方案，
that gets completely confused
它完全被搞糊涂了，
and here is the liquid network solution,
这是液态网络解决方案，
that has the exact same input
它有完全相同的输入，
and has no problem going to to the the going to the robot.
没有问题去找机器人。
Let's see a few more examples here,
让我们再看几个例子，
where we are doing hop by hop,
我们正在一个一个地做，
we're actually searching the object
我们是在搜索物体，
and doing multi step solutions
并做多步解决方案，
and in fact, in fact we can,
事实上，我们可以，
if I can get to my next video,
如果我能看到我的下一个视频，
sorry, so, I,
抱歉，所以，我，
the next one is,
下一个是，
it shows you that we can actually do this forever,
它展示了我们实际上可以永远这样做，
so here is an infinite hop demo,
这是一个无限跳跃的演示，
that was done just outside on the baseball field,
就在外面的棒球场上完成的，
and we, we placed three of the same objects that we trained on
我们放置了三个我们训练过的相同对象，
and we placed them at unknown locations
并将它们放置在未知位置，
and we added the the search feature to our machine learning solution,
然后我们将搜索功能添加到我们的机器学习解决方案中，
and so we can, the system can go on and on and on
所以，系统可以继续运行，
hopping from one to the other.
并从一个跳到另一个。
The final example I will show you is,
我要给你们展示的最后一个例子是，
in is on the patio of the state building,
在圣州大楼的露台上，
where we have put a number of chairs,
我们放了一些椅子，
we have put our favorite chair,
我们放了我们最喜欢的椅子，
but also we have put a lot of other other similar chairs
但我们也放了很多其他类似的椅子，
and we can see that,
我们可以看到，
liquid networks generalize very well,
液态网络的普适性很好，
whereas if we take LSTM solution,
然而，如果我们采用 LSTM 解决方案，
it gets confused and goes to the wrong object.
它会困惑，并到达错误的对象。
So, all of these ideas come together
那么，所有这些想法结合在一起，
to really point to a new type of machine learning,
指向一种新型的机器学习，
that yields models that generalize to unseen scenarios,
这就产生了可以概括到未知场景的模型，
essentially addressing a challenge with today's neural networks,
本质上解决了当今神经网络，
that do not generalize well to unseen test scenarios,
不能很好地概括到未知测试场景的挑战，
because the models are so fast and compact,
因为这些模型是如此快速和紧凑，
you can train them online,
你可以在线上训练它们，
you can train them on edge devices,
你可以在边缘设备上训练它们，
and you can really see that they are beginning to understand the task that they're given,
你可以看到它们开始理解赋予它们的任务，
so you can see that,
所以你可以看到，
we're really beginning to get at the semantics of what these systems,
我们真的开始了解这些系统的语义，
what these systems have to do.
这些系统必须做什么。
So, what does this have to do with the future?
所以，这与未来有什么关系？
I think it is so exciting to use machine learning to study nature
我认为使用机器学习来研究自然是非常令人兴奋的，
and to begin to understand the nature of intelligence
并开始了解智能的本质，
and in our lab here, at csail,
在我们的实验室 csail 中，
we have one project,
我们有一个项目，
that is looking at whether we can understand the lives of whales
看我们是否能够理解鲸鱼的生活，
and so what do I mean by this.
所以我这么说是什么意思。
So here is an example,
所以这是一个例子，
where we have used a robotic drone to, to go very,
我们使用了机器人无人机去做，
sorry this is, this is very loud,
抱歉，这是非常吵的。
we have used a robotic drone to find whales
我们使用机器人无人机来寻找鲸鱼，
and look at what they do
看看它们做了什么，
and track them
并跟踪它们，
and here is some imaging
这是一些图像，
and here some clips from what this what this system is able to do,
这是这个系统能够做的一些剪辑，
we have used machine learning to identify the whales
我们已经使用机器学习来识别鲸鱼，
and then once you have identify the whale,
然后一旦你识别了鲸鱼，
we can actually [servo] to the center of the whale,
我们可以伺服到鲸鱼中心，
essentially tracking the whale along the way,
沿途跟踪鲸鱼，
and here is how, how the system works,
这就是这个系统是如何运作的，
you can you can see a bunch of a group of whales,
你可以看到一群鲸鱼，
and you can see our robot serving and following the whales as they move along.
你可以看到我们的机器人在鲸鱼移动时服务和跟踪它们。
Now, we, this is a very exciting project,
现在，这是一个非常令人兴奋的项目，
because whales are such majestic, intelligent and mysterious creatures,
因为鲸鱼是如此威严、聪明和神秘的生物，
and so if we can use our technologies to get better insights into their lives,
所以，如果我们能够使用我们的技术来更好地了解它们的生活，
we will be able to to understand more about about other animals and other other creatures,
我们就能够更多地了解其他动物和其他生物，
we share this beautiful planet with.
我们共享这个美丽星球。
So we can study these whales from above, from the air,
所以我们可以从空中研究这些鲸鱼，
we can also study the whales from from, within from, from inside the the ocean,
我们也可以大海里面来研究鲸鱼，
and here's here's sophie, our soft robotic fish,
这是 Sophie ，我们的软机器鱼，
with Joseph, who is with us today has participated in in building,
和 Joseph ，今天和我们一起参与建造的，
and here's this beautiful, beautiful, very natural, moving robot,
这是一个漂亮的，非常自然的，移动的机器人，
that can get close to aquatic creatures,
它可以接近水生生物，
that can move in the same way aquatic creatures do,
它可以像水生生物一样移动，
without without disturbing them,
而不会打扰它们，
when you put [] based robots in ocean environments,
当你把机器人放在海洋环境中时，
they behave differently than than the fish do
它们的行为与鱼不同，
and they tend to scare the fish.
它们往往会吓到鱼。
So if you're curious,
所以，如果你好奇，
the tail is made out of silicone
尾巴是由硅胶制成的，
and there is a pump, that can, that can pump water in two of its chambers,
还有一个泵，它可以在它的两个腔室中抽水，
so you see it has two ripped chambers
所以你可以看到它有两个裂开的腔室，
and you can move water from one chamber to the other,
你可以把水从一个腔室转移到另一个腔室，
and depending on how much water we move and in what proportions,
根据我们移动的水量和比例，
you can get the fish to move forward, to turn left or to turn right.
你可以让鱼向前移动，向左转或向右转。
So we can observe the motion of animals using robotic technologies,
所以我们可以使用机器人技术来观察动物的运动，
but we can do more,
但我们可以做得更多，
we can also listen in on what,
我们还可以收听，
oops, actually I need sound here,
糟糕，其实我这里需要声音，
I forgot about this,
我忘了这件事，
we can observe the, the way we can observe what they say to each other,
我们可以观察它们互相说什么的方式，
can you hear?
你能听到吗？
So this is a sperm whale
这是抹香鲸，
and you have heard the vocalization of sperm whales,
你们听到了抹香鲸的叫声，
we believe that, they're talking, that the sperm whale is talking to its family and friends,
我们相信，抹香鲸在和它的家人和朋友说话，
and we would like to know what it's saying,
我们想知道它在说什么，
we have no idea,
我们不知道，
but we can use machine learning to make progress.
但我们可以使用机器学习来取得进展。
And the way we can do that is by, is by
我们可以做到这一点的方法是通过，
using data, using the kind of data you have just heard,
使用你刚刚听到的那种数据，
to look for, to look for the presence of language,
去寻找语言的存在，
which is a major sign of intelligence,
这是智力的一个主要标志，
we can look at whether we have discrete compounds,
我们可以看看我们是否有离散的复合词，
we can look at whether there might be grammar,
我们可以看看是否有语法，
we can look at whether we have long range dependencies,
我们可以看看我们是否有长期依存关系，
we can look at whether we have other properties that human language has.
我们可以看看我们是否有人类语言所具有的其他性质。
And so basically, our project is very much work in progress,
所以，我们的项目正在进行中，
I can't tell you today what the whales are saying to each other,
今天我不能告诉你鲸鱼们在说什么，
but I can tell you that,
但我可以告诉你，
we have made progress,
我们已经取得了进展，
I can tell you that,
我可以告诉你，
we are beginning to find which parts of their calls carry information,
我们开始发现他们通话的哪些部分携带了信息，
we can use machine learning to differentiate the clicks,
我们可以使用机器学习来区分响声，
that allow the whales to echolocate
允许鲸鱼回声定位，
from the clicks that seem to be vocalization and information carrying clicks,
与似乎是发声和携带信息的响声，
we can begin to look at what the protocols for information exchange are,
我们可以开始看看信息交换的协议是什么，
how do they engage in dialogue,
他们如何进行对话，
and we can begin to ask,
我们可以开始问，
what is the information that they say to one another,
他们对彼此所说的信息是什么，
so with our project, we are trying to understand
所以，在我们的项目中，我们试图理解，
the phonetics, the semantics and the syntax and the discourse for whales.
鲸鱼的语音、语义、句法和语篇。
So we have a big dataset consisting of about 22,000 clicks,
我们有一个由大约 22000 次响声组成的大数据集，
the clicks get grouped into [codas],
响声被分组为 coda ，
the codas are like the phonemes,
coda 就像[音素]一样，
and using machine learning,
使用机器学习，
we can identify coda types,
我们可以识别 coda 类型，
we can identify patterns for coda exchanges,
我们可以识别 coda 交换的模式，
and we can begin to really ask ourselves,
我们可以开始真正问自己，
how is it that that whales exchange information.
鲸鱼是如何交换信息的。
And if you're interested in this problem,
如果你对这个问题感兴趣，
please come see us,
请来找我们，
because we have a lot of projects that are very, very exciting
因为我们有很多非常令人兴奋的项目，
and important towards reverse engineering,
对于反向工程很重要，
what this really extraordinary and majestic animal is capable of doing.
这种真正非凡和威严的动物能够做什么。
So let me close by saying that.
让我以此来结束我的演讲。
In this class, you have looked at a number of really exciting machine learning algorithms,
在这节课中，你已经看到了许多非常令人兴奋的机器学习算法，
but you have also looked at what some of the technical challenges with the machine learning algorithms are,
但你也了解了机器学习算法的一些技术挑战，
including data availability,
包括数据可用性，
including data quality,
包括数据质量，
including the amount of computation required, the model size
包括所需的计算量、模型大小，
and the ability of that model to run on edge devices or on huge devices,
以及该模型在边缘设备或大型设备上运行的能力，
you have seen that many of our solutions are black box solutions
你已经看到，我们的许多解决方案都是黑盒解决方案，
and sometimes we have brittle function,
有时我们有脆弱的函数，
we have, we have easily attackable models,
我们有容易受到攻击的模型，
you have also seen some alternative models,
你也看到了一些替代模型，
like liquid networks,
比如液态网络，
which attempt to address some of these questions,
它们试图解决其中的一些问题，
there is so much opportunity for developing improved machine learning,
有如此多的机会来开发改进的机器学习，
using existing models and inventing new models,
利用现有的模型和发明新的模型，
and if we can do this,
如果我们能做到这一点，
we can create an exciting world,
我们就可以创造一个令人兴奋的世界，
where machines will really empower us,
在那里机器将真正增强我们的能力，
will really augment us and enhance us in our cognitive abilities and in our physical abilities.
增强我们的认知能力和身体能力。
So, just imagine,
所以，想象一下，
waking up enabled by your personal assistant,
在你的私人助理的帮助下醒来，
that figures out the optimal time
这会计算出最佳的时间，
and helps you organize all the items that you need for the day
帮助你组织一天所需的所有物品，
and then brings them to you,
然后把它们带给你，
so you don't have to think about whether your outfit matches,
这样你就不必考虑你的服装是否匹配，
and as you walk by a store,
当你走过一家商店时，
the image in the store window displays your picture with the latest fashion on your body,
商店橱窗里的图像会显示你身上的最新时尚照片，
and inside the store,
而在店内，
maybe you want to buy a certain shoe,
也许你想买某一双鞋，
AI system can analyze how you walk,
AI 系统可以分析你的走路方式，
can analyze your your dimensions
可以分析你的尺寸，
and can create a bespoke shoe, a bespoke model just for you,
还可以创建一双定制的鞋子，一个专为你定制的模型，
and then all the, all the clothing,
然后，所以的衣服，
all the items in our environment can kind of awaken,
我们环境中的所有的物品都可以被唤醒，
our clothing could become robots,
我们的衣服可能会变成机器人，
and so our clothing could become monitoring devices,
我们的衣服可以成为监测设备，
but they could also become programmable,
但它们也可以成为可编程的，
for instance, in this case,
例如，在本例中，
you can see the ability of a sweater to change color,
你可以看到毛衣可以改变颜色，
so that the girl can match her friend.
以便女孩可以匹配她的朋友。
Now, this is actually not far fetched,
现在，这实际上并不牵强，
we have a group on campus,
我们在校园里有一个小组，
that is delivering these programmable [fibers],
他们提供这些可编程[光纤]，
that can change color and that they can do some computation.
他们可以变更颜色，它们可以进行一些计算。
At work, inside the intelligent boardroom,
在智能会议室内工作，
the temperature could get adjusted automatically by monitoring people's comfort and gesture,
通过监测人们的舒适度和手势，可以自动调节温度，
and just in time,
假以时日，
holograms could be used to make the virtual world much more, much more realistic,
全息图可以用来让虚拟世界变得更加逼真，
much more connected,
更加相互联系，
and so here they're discussing the the design of a new flying cars,
他们在这里讨论一种新型飞行汽车的设计，
and let's say we have these flying cars
假设我们有这些会飞的汽车，
and then we can integrate these cars with the IT infrastructure,
然后我们可以将这些汽车与 IT 基础设施集成在一起，
the cars will know your needs,
汽车会知道你的需求，
so that they can tell you,
这样它们就可以告诉你，
for instance, that you can buy the plants you have been wanting nearby
比如，你在附近买到你一直想要的植物，
by computing a small detour,
通过计算一个小小的绕道，
and back at home, you can take a first ride on a bike
回到家里，你可以第一次骑自行车，
and the bike itself becomes a robot,
自行车本身就变成了一个机器人，
with adaptable wheels that appear and disappear according to your skill level,
它有可适应的轮子，根据你的技能水平出现和消失，
you can have robots that help with planting,
你可以拥有帮助种植的机器人，
you have, you can have delivery robots
你可以有送货机器人，
and there's the garbage bin, the garbage bin that takes itself out.
还有垃圾桶会自动取出。
And after a good day,
而在美好的一天过后，
when it's time for a bedtime story,
到了睡前讲故事的时候，
you can begin to enter the story
你就可以开始进入故事，
and control the flow
控制流程，
and begin to interact with the characters in the story.
开始与故事中的角色互动。
These are some possibilities for the kind of future,
这些都是未来的一些可能性，
that machine learning, artificial intelligence and robots are enabling,
机器学习、人工智能和机器人所带来的，
and I'm personally very excited about this future,
我个人对这个未来感到非常兴奋，
with robots helping us with cognitive and physical work.
机器人将帮助我们进行认知和体力工作。
But this future is really dependent on very important new advancements,
但是这一未来真的取决于 非常重要的新进展，
that will come from all of you,
你们所能取得的（进展），
and so I'm so excited to see what you will be doing in the next years in the years ahead.
我非常兴奋地看到你们在未来几年将会做些什么。
So thank you very much
所以非常感谢你，
and come work with us.
和我们一起工作吧。